Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 3, Film/TV Projects, 1930-1991; 1936-1987
  - "Freedom Road,", 1944-1958; 1945-1947
    - no title (Box C055)
      - "Freedom Road" -- outline of book -- L.H.; H.F.'s draft of continuity, seq. breakdown -- 1st dr., ca. 1946 (Folder 11)
        Undated story outlines and sequence breakdowns.
      - First seq. breakdown -- notes, 1946; undated (Folder 12)
        Undated "Freedom Road" story outline and first draft of sequence breakdown.
      - Locations, cast etc. -- notes, ca. 1946 (Folder 13)
        Undated "Freedom Road" notes regarding budget revisions, salary estimates, and locations.
      - [Hurwitz, Leo -- correspondence, clippings, 1940s], 1945-1946 (Folder 14)
        Clippings and correspondence regarding "Freedom Road." Includes clippings from the Los Angeles Daily News, The Los Angeles Times, and Hotel & Club Voice regarding the upcoming film adaptation of Freedom Road; and letters from Film Music Associates, artist Gyula Zilzer (with exhibition brochures), Mordecai Gorelik, and Salem Ludwig, inquiring about work on the production. Also includes 10/5/1946 New Dynamo supplement; the 1945 Annual Meteorological Summary; and an envelope from the U.S. Department of Commerce Weather Bureau containing Monthly Meteorological Summaries from 1942-1946.
      - Leo Hurwitz, 1946-1947 (Folder 15)
    - no title (Box C073)
      - Correspondence (General), 1944-1958 (Folder 1)
        Includes a 1944 letter from Eric Burroughs regarding Hurwitz's planned production of Freedom Road; a letter to "Ben" [likely Maddow] regarding Freedom Road.
      - Budget material N.L., "Masters" & misc., 1948; 1950; undated (Folder 22)
        Includes preliminary budgets for "Production #1" [the cast list indicates this is "Freedom Road," not Native Land as indicated by the folder label], "Masters of the Dew", and an unnamed production; an estimate of production costs at RKO Pathe, Inc.; and a comparison of production costs at different studio facilities.
    - no title (Box C226)
      - "Freedom Road" -- first notes, 1946 (Folder 18)
        Handwritten notes; typed draft of Freedom Road Company proposal.
      - CBS and TV -- 1945 (also "Freedom Road"), 1944-1946 (Folder 19)
        Includes CBS rate card; correspondence about "Freedom Road"; letter from Woody Guthrie; program for "The Arts, Sciences, and Professions in the Post-War World"; letter sent from CBS to William Morris about salary for Hurwitz; CBS 1944 annual report (published 1945); personal correspondence; clipping "Television's Growing Pains"
  - Subseries 11, General, 1933-1990; 1942-1986
    - no title (Box C006)
      - [University Network Corporation correspondence, proposal, film treatment], 1974 (Folder 20)
      - [Correspondence, film proposal for “We, the People…”], 1972; 1974 (Folder 21)
    - no title (Box C007)
      - [Envelope labeled: Play-Script “Trial” and misc. TV scripts by others -- late ‘50s, early ‘60s], 1948-1949; 1956; 1964; undated (Folder 4)
        Scripts for “The Trial,” “The Palio of Siena” [for Pan American], "The Barton Children’s TV-Playhouse,” “Forty-Eight Hours,” "The Big Story -- Program 93,” and "Thomas Scherman and the Little Orchestra Present a Television Program of Orchestral Concerts for Children." Also includes a list of 40 Scientific American science programs for television and letters from Charles Pratt and Raymond Sacks.
    - no title (Box C021)
      - China: questions regarding organization, budget, crew, etc., 1971, undated (Folder 24b)
        A list of questions and notes regarding a proposed Chinese film.
      - Notes -- drafts -- China, 1970-1972 (Folder 24c)
        Correspondence, notes, and newspaper articles related to Hurwitz's plans to film a series of documentaries in China related to the book Fanshen by William Hinton.
      - Correspondence -- China, 1971-1975 (Folder 24d)
        Correspondence and notes related to Hurwitz's plans to film a series of documentaries in China related to the book Fanshen by William Hinton.
    - no title (Box C028)
      - [Envelope labeled: "Odyssey" notes], undated (Folder 5)
        Chapter breakdown and an outline for an adaptation of The Odyssey.
    - no title (Box C033)
      - Bulova film: treatment, presentation, budget, 1965; undated (Folder 5)
        Drafts and final versions of notes, treatment, and estimated budget for a revised version of the film The Right Time and the Right Place, sponsored by Bulova watches. Also includes draft of a cover letter to ad agency SSC & B and two technical diagrams of Bulova watch parts mounted on board.
      - Cities idea -- "5 Cities," ideas & budget, undated (Folder 6)
        Notes regarding a film about five cities to be possibly titled "The Cities" or "5 Cities." Includes financial estimates, lists of "Possible Savings" and "American Writers on American Cities," and typed draft of film concept and format.
      - Contacts (jobs) & ideas (random), 1954; 1961-1965; undated (Folder 9)
      - NET correspondence, 1967 (Folder 27)
        Letter from National Educational Television's (NET) Director of Cultural Programs Curtis W. Davis regarding Hurwitz's proposed program "History of American Art."
      - Ideas to develop -- notes, etc., 1961, undated (Folder 29)
        Notes for "Peace Manifesto" dated 1961, possibly later printed as open letters in The New York Times(see clippings in Box C033, Folder 8); undated notes regarding possible film projects, including "Odysseus with puppets in the great outdoors."
      - Leo Hurwitz personal -- from NET, 1965-1966 (Folder 42)
      - Polish film proposal, 1961-1962 (Folder 48)
        Correspondence between Hurwitz, the Polish Ministry of Culture and Art, and the Polish Foreign Ministry regarding proposed films about Poland and atomic war.
      - The July idea! (portable tape idea, RCA), 1963 (Folder 49)
        Drafts, notes, memos, and correspondence between Hurwitz and RCA regarding Hurwitz's ideas for compact audiotape cassettes and portable transistor tape players.
    - no title (Box C036)
      - [Letter to Chaplin, 1959/Verdict for Tomorrow, Eichmann Peabody Award Program/clippings re: Eichmann], 1958-1962; undated (Folder 1)
        Correspondence, including 1959 letter to Charles Chaplin; materials related to Walter McQuade's book When Your Neighborhood Needs a School; a script treatment titled "The Beach and the Man"; and notes for an unnamed project..
    - no title (Box C037)
      - Fortune World Trade, 1958-1959 (Folder 1b.1)
        Materials related to the film The New Age of World Commerce, including script draft, shooting script, and list of "scenes to be secured from miscellaneous sources"; shot lists and lists of categories and films seen; completion schedule; drafts of related correspondence; a handwritten note.
    - no title (Box C040)
      - The Education Council, 1966-1967 (Folder 4)
      - Charge account -- Leo Hurwitz Productions, Inc. -- letters on possible Einstein film, 1958 (Folder 43)
    - no title (Box C041)
      - Einstein film project, 1984-1986 (Folder 25)
        Notes and correspondence between Hurwitz and the American Friends of Hebrew University regarding a film about Albert Einstein. Also includes letters from Robin Briehl containing notes from a meeting related to the project, and the Motion Picture Editors Local 771 regarding their upcoming relocation.
      - Metropolitan Museum film project, 1981-1982 (Folder 45)
        Notes of meeting with Karl Katz of the Met regarding a proposed series of films about the museum's masterpieces; list of "100 Treasures of the Met" with cover letter from Katz.
      - Miners (from Josh), 1978-1981 (Folder 52)
        Material related to Hurwitz's Miners Film Project (working title), including project prospectus; a letter from Hurwitz to Moe Asch of Folkways Records confirming Asch's investment; log of film rushes; project overview with Josh Karan's contact information; letter from the Film Fund agreeing to act as fiscal agent for the film; and a program proposal submitted to the Corporation for Public Broadcasting 11/13/1980. Also includes January 1981 issue of the United Mine Workers' paper Coal Field Defender.
    - no title (Box C043)
      - Recent correspondence, 1961-1962 (Folder 3b)
        Business correspondence, including a receiving notice from Bonded Storage regarding 35mm print of The Museum and the Fury; breakdowns of Here at the Waters' Edge expenses(film accounts); draft of a letter to Film Frontiers, Inc., stockholders; letter from Hurwitz to Robert Jungk about a film adaptation of his book Brighter than a Thousand Suns; letters regarding the distribution of The Museum and the Fury.
      - Peace thru Law, 1963 (Folder 3h)
    - no title (Box C045)
      - For Detroit, 1943-1944 (Folder 10b)
        Material for a potential film for the United Auto Workers, including notes on expenses, correspondence, and budget.
      - Documents, 1942-1945 (Folder 10c)
        Documents related to income tax; application for federal employment; letter from the Office of War Information (OWI) confirming completion of employment; contract signed by Paul Strand and Leo Hurwitz employing the William Morris Agency as representative and advisor; copies of contract between Hurwitz and Vanguard Films; notes.
      - Ideas for films, etc., 1943-1944 (Folder 10i)
        Notes on film ideas for Office of War Information (OWI), General Motors, and CBS (on the subject of television), as well as general ideas for films.
      - War Report from the People, 1944 (Folder 10j)
        Résumé, summary, and budget for "By the People"; correspondence with the William Morris Agency and Screen Writer's Guild; correspondence from Pendleton Dudley about newspaper ad buys; and correspondence about an idea for an anthology film originating from conversation with Paul Strand described as "War Report from the People."
      - Current ideas at work, 1944 (Folder 10k)
        Outline for a course in documentary film; notes; ideas for a film about a wounded solider; letter from William Esty and Company
      - For coast -- data and to do, 1942-1943 (Folder 10l)
        Correspondence with 20th Century Fox regarding Hurwitz and Strand's work on a film about Dr. Norman Bethune and an adaptation of Robert Carse's There Go the Ships. Also includes correspondence from Joris Ivens mentioning the aborted Merchant Marine film and notes.
      - Misc., 1943-1945 (Folder 10o)
    - no title (Box C050)
      - "Lonesome Train" prospectus, 1952-1955, undated (Folder 7)
      - Films: Dr.-patient relations, 1953 (Folder 12)
        Contains correspondence and notes related to the production of medical films, including a film about doctor-patient relations. Includes contact information; budget notes; paper on health education by George Rosen, MD; press materials, catalog, and article about public and mental health films; documents related to a 7/4/1953 of screening of "the first HIP film" (most likely Hurwitz's short On This Day).
      - Films: ideas & notes -- misc., 1953-1954; undated (Folder 17)
        Ideas for films and film series, including a film about the H-bomb and scientific research. Includes a reprint of the "Scientists and Other Citizens," a talk given by Gerard Piel.
      - Films prod. -- "Which Way Out" -- Oberndorf, 1949-1950 (Folder 18)
        Documents regarding a film adaptation of C.P. Oberndorf's book of short stories Which Way Way Out, including letters from Oberndorf, Morris Helprin; a one-year option agreement for production rights. Includes a 2/5/1949 Saturday Review review of Which Way Way Out.
      - Film: Rheingold, 1952 (Folder 20)
        Notes, correspondence, shot lists, and schedules regarding a sponsored film about Rheingold beer.
      - Film -- Sholom Aleichem, 1954 (Folder 21)
        Correspondence and notes related to a film version of the play The World of Sholom Aleichem. Includes a letter from Howard Da Silva a theater program.
    - no title (Box C055)
      - Misc -- schedule; budget summaries, etc., 1959 (Folder 18k)
        Budgets, lists of expenditures, draft of production schedule, and list of documentary material for "Museums of the World."
    - no title (Box C058)
      - [Envelope labeled: NET Portr. of a Nazi], undated (Folder 21)
    - no title (Box C068)
      - [Proposal for the use of film in dance curriculum], 1968 (Folder 9d)
    - no title (Box C073)
      - Films -- production forms, budget forms, 1946; 1950-1951; 1956 (Folder 21)
        Budget notes and correspondence for film projects including The Key; "Ballet Ballads"; a film about rug cleaning for the Lincoln Rug Co.; "France Film" [possibly Voici la France]; and a "home furnishing show. Also includes blank production and requisition forms from Paramount Pictures and International Pictures; shooting schedule, production breakdown, and call sheets for Heaven Only Knows; and shooting schedules and call sheets for several Columbia Pictures productions. Also includes the booklet "Working Rules of the Association of Documentary and Television Film Cameramen"; a 1956 letter from Rose Hurwitz regarding the division of expenses for mother's care; and a blank employer-National Association of Broadcast Engineers and Technicians CIO contract.
      - Budget material N.L., "Masters" & misc., 1948; 1950; undated (Folder 22)
      - Films -- doc. film scripts (others), 1944; 1956; undated (Folder 23)
        Includes scripts for the documentary film projects "Patrol Bomber," "Boy Meets Plane" [aka Tomorrow We Fly],There Shall Be Freedom,Freedom of the American Road, and a summary for a project titled "The Quaker."
    - no title (Box C086)
      - Harmonica BRDN -- budget, undated (Folder 20)
        Budget for a 16mm color sound film, "3 minutes plus titles."
    - no title (Box C096)
      - Class material (recent), 1963 (Folder 17e)
        Shooting script for "Peace Commercial"; Peace Commercial drafts; script for two peace commercials; poem "Reflections on Memorials to the Glorious Dead"; draft of the commercial by Manfred Kirchheimer; general notes on the project.
    - no title (Box C102)
      - Hollywood towards job, 1942-1944 (Folder 13)
      - [Envelope labeled: Buffalo Media Study material, etc.], 1956-1965 (Folder 16)
        Contrary to the envelope label there are no materials related to the State University of New York at Buffalo's Department of Media Study. Folder contains correspondence regarding Patterns of a Profession; screening Here at the Waters' Edge; puppet films; a film about Albert Einstein; and the "New Age of World Trade" film project for Fortune magazine. Other correspondents include Charles Pratt regarding a film titled "New York Island"; Charles Chaplin (from Hurwitz); and Walt Kelly, regarding an adaptation of Pogo.
    - no title (Box C104)
      - [Folder labeled:Birth of World-- Transfilm, 1955-1956 (Folder 14g)
        Includes materials related to Zachary Taylor's 1958 film The Earth Is Born, the first in a planned film series based on the Life magazine science series The World We Live In. Includes narration script, cover letter from Life, list of consultants, comments, and notes.
      - Dialogue with a Woman Departed-- new work, general notes: letters, 1980 (Folder 15f)
        Notes regarding Dialogue with a Woman Departed lab work and soundtrack. Also includes correspondence with the Hollywood Museum regarding Native Land material and Goddard College about Do You Know a Man Named Goya?
    - no title (Box C108)
      - Film: "Peace Will Win", 1950-1951 (Folder 2)
        Materials related to Joris Ivens and Jerzy Szelubksi's film Peace Will Win, including synch and timing log, script, notes on general problems with the film, and suggestions for revisions. Also includes "A Program of New Polish Films" from the Polish Embassy, which included Peace Will Win, and the pamphlet "Poland in the Camp of Peace."
      - ["The Story Behind the Picture" -- script], ca. 1950 (Folder 3c)
        Script for "The Story Behind the Picture," a planned half-hour weekly show featuring interviews conducted by Bosley Crowther. Hurwitz is not featured; the main topic seems to be The Third Man.
      - [Children's Village material; personal bill, correspondence about work], 1950 (Folder 3d)
        Includes a case docket for the Children's Village children's home in Dobbs Ferry, NY. Also includes a promotional booklet, a young government constitution, a case conference study, a personal bill, and correspondence from Adams & Co. Real Estate regarding possible television work.
      - Short story, 1948; 1950 (Folder 3e)
        Material related to a proposed program titled "The Short Story Theater," including an outline for a presentation, with memo from Souvaine Co.; a breakdown of estimated costs; list of stories; and comments copied to Souvaine and Hurwitz. Also includes suggestions for players and directors available for This Is My Best dated 1948.
      - ["Ah! Sweet Mystery!" production materials], 1950 (Folder 3g)
        Materials related to the radio production "Ah! Sweet Mystery!", including notes, audition script, and an itemized breakdown of costs.
      - "Jack Dempsey's Gym", 1950 (Folder 5b)
        Materials related to the proposed television program "Jack Dempsey's Gym," including budget estimates, program outline, and lists of boxers.
      - Visifex, 1950 (Folder 5c)
      - Telebingo script, 1950 (Folder 5f)
        Script for Telebingo program.
      - Notes on shows, 1950 (Folder 5h)
        Materials related to television productions, including Musical Playhouse cast and credits; schedule for Opera Television Theatre; Telebingo budget, production notes, and reactions; "Short Story Theatre" production notes; "This is My Best" budget; and "What Do You Want?" notes.
    - no title (Box C160)
      - Original selected -- first 4 reels, undated (Folder 10)
        Outline of an unnamed film, with numbered reels and scenes featuring artworks.
      - Miners film project, ca. 1980 (Folder 27)
    - no title (Box C172)
      - TV -- live ideas, 1948-1951 (Folder 6)
        Ideas for television programs. Includes a script for a program of concerts for young people, and notes on "The Yankee Doodler" and a dance program.
      - TV scripts -- Gilford, Savo, undated (Folder 8)
        Scripts for "The Pantomime Theater" starring Jimmy Savo, and "The Jack Gilford Show" written by Mort Levin and Bob Stewart.
      - Projects under way (Pratt), 1954-1955 (Folder 13)
        Letter from Charles Pratt confirming Hurwitz's involvement in a television series about festivals, to be presented to Pan American Airways or another airline. Includes an outline of a film about the Palio di Siena.
      - Museum film project (Ford Fund for Advancement of Education), 1956-1957 (Folder 17)
        Includes correspondence between Hurwitz, Gilbert Seldes, Charles Pratt, MIT, and Smith College regarding a series educational films about the history of art. Also includes correspondence, notes, press materials, and publications related to the 3rd International Art Film Festival.
      - Museum film project -- Metropolitan Museum, 1951-1957 (Folder 20)
        Correspondence and notes related to Hurwitz's proposal for a "History of Art on Film" project. Correspondents include the Metropolitan Museum of Art; Oliver Larkin (Smith College); Helmut von Erffa; MIT; the Fogg Art Museum; the National Gallery of Art; Indiana University; and the Whitney Museum of American Art.
      - Memoranda, 1957-1958 (Folder 21)
    - no title (Box C176)
      - [Film library catalogs], 1947; undated (Folder 4)
        Includes catalogs from the PCW [Pennsylvania College for Women] Film Service (1947-1948 catalog), the Photo and Film Department of the National Audubon Society, and Heidenkamp Nature Pictures ("Birds of North America").
      - ["Commentary for Use with Birds of North America" I], undated (Folder 5)
        Four commentary guides for use with Heidenkamp Nature Pictures' educational film series "Birds of North America." Includes multiple photocopied pages, with alphanumeric markers.
      - ["Commentary for Use with 'Birds of North America'" II], undated (Folder 6)
        Photocopied pages from commentary guides used with Heidenkamp Nature Pictures' educational film series "Birds of North America," with alphanumeric markers.
      - ["Commentary for Use with 'Birds of North America'" III], undated (Folder 7)
    - no title (Box C185)
      - [File Pocket Labeled: Art film history project -- Hurwitz, Pratt], 1952; ca. 1957-1959 (Folder 3)
        Bound prospectus for "American Art in Films," a proposed film series on the history of American art. Also includes responses to the prospectus; questions for Professor Larkin at Smith College; price lists for film printing; budget items; production notes and schedule; blank budget form from the International Movie Producers' Service; and reports on scenes.
    - no title (Box C186)
      - [Envelope labeled:Alice in Wonderland-- cartoon feature script], ca. 1933 (Folder 5)
        Scripts for Alice in Wonderland and The Heroes by Jay Leyda and Leo Hurwitz.
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes -- documents, production #5 --Native Land], 1936-1938 (Folder 9)
        Includes Native Land sequence draft and storyboard sketch; notes; pamphlets and memos regarding civil liberties, anti-labor activities, industrial spies, and labor; correspondence regarding a Consumers Union film; a court document regarding the United Automobile Workers; and an International Labor Defense yearbook for 1936-1937.
    - no title (Box C190)
      - ["American Comrades" script], undated (Folder 26)
        Undated script for film project "American Comrades," subtitled "Script I -- The Hard Line." Richard Wormser's name and telephone number appear in red ink on the cover.
    - no title (Box C192)
      - [Envelope labeled: Notes, etc. of '30s -- early Frontier], 1937-1939 (Folder 2b)
        Includes an outline for an anti-Fascist animated film; statement by Joris Ivens on Paul Strand;Native Land summary; two-ring binder embossed with "Victory" on the cover containing sequences for film labeled "Prologue -- XX -- Song of the School-Children," with notes on child labor film ("Pay Day"), brochure on Frontier Films, notes on steel workers film, sketch for unnamed scenario, notes on laissez-faire, notes on school film (all tucked into the front of the binder).
    - no title (Box C201)
      - [Unlabeled envelope with "Miners" grant application], 1978 (Folder 12)
        Photocopy of a National Endowment for the Arts project grant application for Hurwitz's documentary about the Gillespie, IL, miners' strike.
    - no title (Box C226)
      - [Theatre Workshop journal, Oct.-Dec. 1936 issue; "Black Legion" notes], undated (Folder 1)
        Includes notes for a film about the 1936 murder of Charles A. Poole by the Black Legion vigilante group.
      - ["Panic & Promise" series proposal], 1990 (Folder 10)
        Proposal for a nine-part series titled "Panic & Proposal: America and the Great Depression" to be produced by Blackside Inc., including a cover letter and list of questions for Hurwitz.
      - Dance, 1944-1945 (Folder 12)